Richard James Dyce, MA Cantab MIET FRSA

Details	
Marital Status	Married, 2 children
Email Address	dd@dyce.com
Mobile	+44 (0) 7712 828860
Other	Clean driving licence
LinkedIn	http://www.linkedin.com/in/rjdyce

Summary

I enjoy working with people, helping them to understand and solve their problems.

Skills & Expertise

A commercial FileMaker developer since 1993. Through a first-hand practical understanding of successful business practice, and an academic grounding in computing science, I have provided essential process development, implementation, and refinement to enterprise and SME clients in a variety of business spheres, from multi-national oil field service companies to steroid research suppliers, national magazine publishers to international property groups. Tools I have written produce the monthly vehicle listings at the back of TopGear Magazine, 400+ page catalogues in InDesign, template-based documents for financial web-marketing companies, and static websites for music charities.

Proficient in a wide range of development tools and cross-platform environments: from shell scripting (bash, VB & Python), through compiler- based, and off-the- shelf applications. I have developed mission critical applications on LAMP stacks (MySQL, PHP5, Javascript & jQuery), using database products (FileMaker, Omnis, Access), and rapid application development tools (AppleScript studio, VBA).

I am a quick-study, and enjoy the challenge of a new language/environment.

Experience

Dyce & Sons Ltd

Director

April 2013 - Present (2 years 3 months)

Dyce & Sons provides business consultancy, process management, training, and bespoke software, database, and web application design to SME businesses throughout the UK. It is the Scotland-based continuance of the previously England-based Richard Dyce Consultants Ltd., working with the same client- base, and providing the same range of services.

Recent contracts undertaken include:

DePuy Synthes Companies, Switzerland

February 2016 - Present (1 yr 4 months)

Senior Developer, working in a German-speaking environment on CAPA Remediations and new functionality for Large-scale MDM translation system.

Developed a generic FileMaker native, low impact, drop-in audit tool to augment the functionality of the existing Synthes MDM solution. The tool is fully documented, with installation instructions, performance tests suites, and Unit test suites in FileMaker. Provided a similarly designed secure document storage to replace the Windows-managed document system. Implemented optimisations for backend processing between SAP and FileMaker using innovative virtual list techniques, functional coding, and scheduled VB scripts.

Wates Group Ltd: Maintenance & Mentoring

August 2015 - January 2016 (6 months)

This was a 3-month initial contract that was extend to 6 months.

Reviewed & refactored their internal systems. This was a windows based environment with a large amount of DevOps work, including automation of FTP, batch scripted file processing, multi-server cloud-based FileMaker development, and deployment to 3 new client contracts with remote PDA access. Specifically:

- Filemaker development across their current application suite
- Interpreted of change requests and developed changes within the test environment
- Deployed of changes to Production environments through Change Management
- Assisted in maintaining of system related documentation
- Assisted in the remedying of break/fix calls coming through the service desk

Knowledge Transfer Network (KTN): Maintenance & Mentoring

October 2014 - June 2015 (9 months)

This was a 3-month initial contract that was extend to 9 months.

Reviewed & refactored their internal systems DB, which provides work planning and HR functions for the enterprise, and also forms the backend to one of their extranet services. Refactoring involved:

- replacement of 100+ scripts with generic, 20 or parameterised versions;
- introduction of ExecuteSQI-type techniques to simplify the table structures;
- a parameterised reporting tool, for building user-specific, recordable reports;
- a HighCharts-based graphing UI for measuring staff loading KPIs;
- · a template-based tool for Email handling;
- a template-based tool for generating KPI reports as PDFs;
- · adding documentation to existing scripts and layouts; and
- the addition of roll-out schedule tool for controlled testing and deployment of new features, fixes.

In addition, I wrote training materials for their in-house development team in order to ensure that the new techniques and tools will be kept in play after my departure.

Schlumberger Oilfields UK Ltd.: Business System & Maintenance

2009 - Present (8 years)

This contract has run from 2009, where I was initially brought in to clean-up a basic v.5 FileMaker database of job notes. I was then asked to specify and develop a complete information management system to run their entire Aberdeen Completions operation. The system now comprises:

- Quality Control Plan (QCP) and Work Instructions (WI) for three separate segments QCPs consist of multiple WIs, with each task performed covered by a WI, Pre- and Post-job records, Client Satisfaction Reports, Well & Rig data sheets;
- Goods Received Notices (GRNs) for electronically signing for deliveries, managing Technical Reception of parts, notifying engineers of parts arrivals, and measuring KPIs;
- Equipment Transfers for tracking movement of goods within the enterprise;
- Assignment Tool for managing engineer assignments between clients;
- Quotes, Proposals and Tenders tool, for generating versioned PDF quotes by tying Word & Excel directly into FileMaker via VisualBasic macros;
- · Order Purchase Tracking for managing production of parts in other SLB sites; and
- Forecasting Tool, for producing forecasts and rolling forecasts with a TimeMachine-style interface for reviewing previous forecast states.

The contract has been in maintenance mode for over a year now, at one day per month.

Aberdeen Music Festival: X-Platform Publishing Tool

December 2014 - June 2015

This was a short-term, time-sensitive contract for a local charity, based in Aberdeen. They required a tool that would allow them to produce their syllabus, programme, and website in-house. The tool allows them to create and manage:

- the data for sections and classes for performers, edit & preview the website using Markdown;
- PDF ads, and their layout for inclusion in the syllabus and programmes;
- · the syllabus PDF itself for printing or downloading;
- the static website, including pages, sections, and PayPal information, and automated synching with the remote web server from within FileMaker; and
- the programme PDF itself which runs to 100+ pages, including front & back materials, Ad sections, and is indexed by class;

Richard Dyce Consultants Ltd.

Director

October 2003 - April 2013 (9 years 7 months)

SME Business consultancy, providing network and application support, training, data cleaning and bespoke FileMaker & LAMP (MAMP) web application design and implementation. Designed ground-up cross-client PHP-based CMS, for standalone operation, or synced with FileMaker data entry/reporting tools.

Goode International

External Consultant

1999 - December 2011 (12 years)

Provided on-going technical support and purchasing advice.

Macworld

Freelance Writer

2003 - 2006 (3 years)

Freelance - Various

Technical Consultant

February 1996 - October 2003 (7 years 9 months)

Clients included Baker Oil Tools, Camco, FileMaker Inc, EMAP Metro, Sykes Cottages, Camelot, Goode International, Judy Bennet PR, BSA, and Simon & Schuster Publishing. Retained by Mediamation Ltd., Bibliocraft etc. as General Programming Consultant. Network Consultancy. Example work;

* Multi-user Macintosh-based sales system.

Automated WWW FileMaker database publishing systems for Steraloids Inc. and Instant Access Ltd. * Multi-user Windows-based Course logging system for Nivation Ltd. in FileMaker.

- * Designed and implemented bespoke client, property & customer management tool for large holiday property company, replacing 1,200 square feet of wall planners with PHP/MySQL web-based client UI.
- * Designed and implemented catalogue publishing tool for specialist chemicals reseller leading to 50% sales improvement. Commissioned by Microsoft/Apple to write 420 page training book for Word.
- * Presented document publishing demonstrations for FileMaker using FileMaker, Quark & AppleScript at their Stamford Bridge conference.

Gray's School of Art, Robert Gordon University, Aberdeen

University Researcher

June 1994 - February 1996 (1 year 9 months)

Lecturer in CAD/CAM and design theory for Design for Industry BA Hons course. Research primarily concerned with the interface design and technical issues relating to the assembly and construction of an Electronic Media Journal based on CD-ROM distribution technology, such as acquisition and distribution of material using the Internet, and the construction of a cross-platform multimedia publishing tool-set.[Pre-WWW]

Instant Access

Technical Manager

January 1993 - June 1994 (1 year 6 months)

Project Manager for (then) unique CD-ROM based program delivery system. Liaised with programming teams to design, specify, test, and implement complex encryption/decryption multimedia package, overseeing group of 5 programmers. Developed on-line Omnis customer/purchase database with AppleEvent links to external client servers. [Pre-WWW]

Dennis Publishing

MIS Manager

August 1991 - January 1993 (1 year 6 months)

Sole responsibility for 200+ user publishing system for magazine publisher of 11 computer/hardware magazines. Implemented company move from three building site into re-furbished single five floor building. Designed and supervised installation of networking, telephony, and electrical services. Chairman of Dennis Technical Group.

MacUser Magazine

Technical Editor

July 1990 - August 1991 (1 year 2 months)

Responsible for writing and commissioning technical features and articles for twice monthly magazine.

Education

University of Cambridge

MA Engineering Tripos I, Computer Science Tripos II

Publications

Journeys Through Microsoft Word 5.1 (The Macintosh Guide), Addison-Wesley June 1, 1993

Organizations

- Institution of Engineering & Technology, February 2009 to Present
- BCS February 2006 February 2009

Languages

- Basic German
- Basic French

Skills

Programming

- PHP 5.x (& unit testing)
- Filemaker Pro 3.x 13.x
- Javascript, jQuery 2.x, coffeescript
- Python
- MySQL
- Unix shell scripting (bash)
- AppleScript
- XML & XSLT
- Markdown & Multimarkdown
- HTML, CSS, Less, Sass, Twitter Bootstrap
- Remote server admin
- Win XP, Win 7, MacOS X
- ER Modelling
- Regular Expressions

General

- Technical Writing
- Public Speaking
- Technical Training
- Feature Writing
- Conference Presentations
- Technical Illustration